Whereas an AND keyword further filters
information in a WHERE clause, the OR
keyword expands the possible number of records
returned within a query. For example, take this
query where a criterion has been added to
filter this list to show only people in Los
Angeles. I will execute this, and we have 91 rows.
Suppose we want people from both Los Angeles and
Long Beach. At this point, we really need to
analyze what people say they want against how
we need to build a query. What if we put the AND
keyword here and then added City = 'Long Beach'.
Would this work? In executing this,
clearly, this did not work. Why? Because
no person in this list will be in both Los Angeles
and Long Beach, at least, not in the same record.
For this criteria piece, we need an OR clause.
Literally, this means the person can be in Los
Angeles, or the person can be in Long Beach.
I will execute this, and we have 186 rows now,
about double what we had before. Before leaving
this topic, what if we have situations where
AND and OR clauses need to be used? For example,
what if we now wanted to limit this list to anyone
in either city but with a last name of Cox?
Watch what happens as I add an AND clause here,
set the LastName to Cox, and then execute this.
We still have 93 people. Why? Because this is
literally saying the city can be Los Angeles,
or this could be someone with the last name
of Cox living in Long Beach. In other words,
you could put parentheses around this piece of
the query, and the results would be the same.
That said, we want the query to analyze the
city portion first and then the last name. Thus,
I will put parentheses around
the city portion of the criteria,
execute this again, and now
we have just three people.
For multiple criteria in AND/OR situations,
treat the criteria like you would a math problem
and put parentheses around that which
you want to treat as a single criterion.